<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://saramaiah.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://saramaiah.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-02-25T06:45:32+00:00</updated><id>https://saramaiah.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Personal website for Sara Ramaiah, research assistant at CWRU. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Introduction</title><link href="https://saramaiah.github.io/blog/2025/introduction/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction"/><published>2025-02-24T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-24T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://saramaiah.github.io/blog/2025/introduction</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saramaiah.github.io/blog/2025/introduction/"><![CDATA[<p>Hello! This is my first post on this blog, and a bit of an introduction. My name is Sara, and while I consider myself a computational biologist now, I’m fairly new to the field. I studied biochemistry in undergrad, and then joined a lab where I did mainly standard molecular biology, mouse handling, and tissue culture work. I then started work on a single cell RNA sequencing project, which started me down the rabbit hole of bioinformatics and computational biology.</p> <p>I’ve spent a lot of time working on making the tools that I work with stable and approachable to others, and it’s this work that I hope to share via my GitHub page and this blog. I owe a lot of this to the open-source software and Linux communities. I use Linux for my personal computer as well as my workstation now because of how comfortable I am with it, and I’ve started taking on programming projects for fun. Given the right resources, I believe that anyone who wants to learn (anything from basic Python tools to custom high-performance computing pipelines) can absolutely do it.</p> <p>I’ll be adding more to the blog over time, but in the meantime, I’d like to link some helpful resources for getting started in different topics.</p> <h4 id="the-basics">The Basics</h4> <ul> <li><a href="https://linuxhandbook.com/">Linux Handbook</a>: A very comprehensive set of guides and tutorials for getting familiar with the command line and bash scripting, as well as other common utilities (Vim, Git, Docker, Kubernetes, etc.). While most of the resources are free, there are some that require a paid membership ($50 annually).</li> <li><a href="https://training.linuxfoundation.org/training/introduction-to-linux/">Introduction to Linux</a>: A free course published by The Linux Foundation designed to introduce people comfortable with other computers (i.e. Windows, MacOS) to Linux, both at the practical and conceptual levels.</li> <li><a href="https://leetcode.com/">LeetCode</a>: A tool for problem-based learning across many areas in computer science. I’m lumping this one in with the basics because I think that learning by doing is way more important than learning by reading. LeetCode (or other similar platforms) can help you practice new skills at basically any level until you’re ready to start working on real projects.</li> </ul> <h4 id="nix">Nix</h4> <ul> <li><a href="https://zero-to-nix.com/">Zero to Nix</a>: Guide to the Nix language and package manager, both at a practical and conceptual level.</li> <li><a href="https://nixos-and-flakes.thiscute.world/">NixOS and Flakes Book</a>: Unofficial guide to NixOS and Flakes that I find to be much more approachable than the official documentation.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[first post on the new blog!]]></summary></entry></feed>